[Music]
a positive integer is said to be perfect
if it is equal to the sum of its proper
divisors
for example here's the number six with
its proper divisors two three and one
and here's the number 28 with its proper
divisors 4 14 2 7 and 1. we can see that
6 is equal to 1 plus 2 plus 3 and 28 is
equal to one plus two plus four plus
seven plus fourteen therefore both 6 and
28 are perfect numbers
separated by about 2000 years Euclid and
Euler proved the two halves of the
theorem that states that n is an even
perfect number if and only if n can be
written as the form 2 raised to the
quantity P minus 1 multiplied by 2 to
the P minus 1 where 2 to the P minus 1
is prime according to this theorem if n
is an even perfect number we can arrange
n dots in a rectangle with Dimensions 2
raised to the P minus 1 and 2 to the P
minus one but then the side of length 2
to the P minus 1 can be split into two
pieces one of length two raised to the P
minus 1 and the other with a length of 2
raised to the P minus 1 minus one now
consider the Triangular array with base
of length 2 raised to the P minus 1
minus 1 sitting in the upper right of
this rectangle we can swing this array
down forming a larger triangular array
in this case the base of the new
triangular array is 2 to the P minus 1
plus 2 to the P minus 1 minus one which
simplifies to 2 to the P minus 1 but
this means that any even perfect number
can fit into a triangular array with a
base of length 2 to the P minus 1. so
that n is an even perfect number if and
only if n is the 2 to the P minus 1
triangular number where 2 to the P minus
1 is prime it turns out that there
aren't many primes of the form 2 to the
P minus 1 that we know these primes are
called mercen primes and it's an open
problem to figure out if there are
infinitely many such primes equivalently
it's an open problem to figure out if
there are infinitely many even perfect
numbers
foreign